Register of the World War II subject collection
Hoover Institution Archives
World War II subject collection
1939-2004
XX740
Hoover Institution Archives
94 manuscript boxes, 4 card file boxes, 4 oversize boxes, 1 oversize folder, 10 videocassettes, 2 sound discs, memorabilia (39.2 linear feet)
Leaflets, pamphlets, proclamations, clippings, propaganda, manuals, other printed matter, letters, reports, memoranda, maps, memorabilia, and miscellany relating to military operations and home front conditions in many countries during World War II, including material on military occupations, prisoners of war, and forced labor. Also includes material on resistance movements in various countries, especially France.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Use copies of some sound recordings in this collection are available for immediate access. To listen to other sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives over various years.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Leaflets, pamphlets, proclamations, clippings, propaganda, manuals, other printed matter, letters, reports, memoranda, maps, memorabilia, and miscellany relating to military operations and home front conditions in many countries during World War II, including material on military occupations, prisoners of war, and forced labor. Also includes material on resistance movements in various countries, especially France.
Prisoners of war.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Conscript labor.; World War, 1939-1945--Occupied territories.; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.; World War, 1939-1945--France.; Sound recordings.; Video tapes.
- Subject File, 1936-1994 (Boxes 1-57)
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical notes, broadsides, brochures, bulletins, cartoons, correspondence, diaries, flyers, forms, handbooks, identification papers, instructions, leaflets, lists, manuals, maps, memoirs, memoranda, newsletters, official documents, orders, pamphlets, photographs, postcards, posters, press releases, proclamations, propaganda, ration cards, regulations, reports, rosters, serial issues, studies, underground literature, writings, clippings and other printed matter, and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by country and then by subject or physical form.
  - General
    - Censorship, 1939-1945 (Box 49)
      Envelopes opened by the censor addressed to the Hoover Library, Stanford, California.
    - Churches, undated (Box 46)
      Pamphlets relating to the attitude of the Churches vis-a-vis fascism and nazism.
    - Civilian relief, 1944 (Box 47)
      Pamphlet issued by the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration, entitled UNRRA: Organization, Aims and Progress.
    - Commemorations, 1994 (Box 57)
      Programs, booklets, pamphlets, brochures, serial issues, and memorabilia relating to the commemorations of the fiftieth anniversaries of the D-Day landings in Normandy and of the Battle of the Bulge.
    - Diplomatic history (Box 48)
      - Origins of the war, 1937-1938, 1940-1955
        Pamphlets relating to the origins of the war. Includes a compilation of documents from the period 1937-1938. In English and Polish.
      - Conferences, 1942 December 18 (Box 46)
        Proceedings of the Round Table Conference "Germany's Thirty Years' War" held at the Savoy Hotel, London.
    - Governments-in-exile, 1942-1943 (Box 48)
      Pamphlet by Edward Puacz relating to various exiled governments and pamphlets issued by the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace relating to European governments-in-exile.
    - Jews, pamphlets (Box 46)
      - General, Justice for the Jews and The Jews in the Family of Nations, 1943
      - American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee, 1941-1943 (Box 53)
      - World Jewish Congress, 1943-1944
    - Military operations, 1945 (Box 48)
      Chart of operations in the European Theater.
    - Propaganda (Boxes 1-4, 45, 50-52)
      - Allied
        - General, 1939-1945
          Pamphlets, leaflets, and reports, in a variety of languages, distributed by the Allied Forces in Europe, Asia, and the Arab world.
        - French propaganda leaflets (in German), including a pamphlet by Hermann Rauschning denouncing Hitler; and British air raid leaflets (in English, French and German) dropped by the R.A.F., as well as other leaflets relating to the paper salvage campaign in Great Britain (Box 4)
        - American pamphlet issued by the U.S. Office of War Information entitled Modern Leaflet Bombing, 1945 (Box 47)
        - Printing plate used for leaflets dropped on Japanese cities several days ahead of bombing, advising citizens to evacuate (Box 43)
      - Axis (Boxes 5-6)
        - General, 1939-1945
          Mostly German propaganda, in various languages, distributed in Europe and Asia. Includes one issue of Front und Heimat (German soldier's newspaper).
        - Pamphlets issued by the German authorities in Poland, 1940-1942 (Box 48)
        - Leaflet distributed after the Japanese Army landed in Indonesia, 1942 (Box 6)
    - Reconstruction (Box 53)
      - General, 1942-1945
        Pamphlets, brochures, and speeches, including on world organization and world peace. Includes Richard N. Coudenhove-Kalergi, "Peace Aims as War Weapons," Martha Jelenko, Post-War Reconstruction: Major Programs and Opinions, and Wm. Reitmann, Lasting World Peace and Total World-Disarmament on a Divine-Angelic Basis. Also includes a report by the Women's Employment Federation on post-war opportunities for women.
      - Europe, 1955-1957
        Clippings by Paul van Zeeland and others relating to his activities to secure European peace and union. Includes an undated typescript on his wartime activities and the book jacket for Paul van Zeeland au service de son temps.
    - Refugees, 1946
      Williams, Pierce, "Preliminary Summary of Report on Refugees and Displaced Persons: An Urgent United Nations Problem."
    - Trade unions, 1943 (Box 46)
      Pamphlet published by the Mutual Defense League containing a speech and articles by Isidore Nagler relating to the role of labor in the struggle against fascism and the problems facing the international trade union movement.
    - Miscellany (Boxes 1, 44)
      - General, 1941-1948
        Pamphlets, leaflets, ordinances, and other printed matter relating to various aspects of World War II and its aftermath, and reports (in German and in English) relating mainly to resistance activities in German-occupied Europe.
      - Anti-fascist poem by Eolo Montevideo, 1944 (Box 46)
  - Austria, undated
    Pamphlet published by Freiheit fur Osterreich, entitled Austria's Freedom Front: Manifesto of the Austrian Underground Movement.
  - Balkan Peninsula, 1941-1944 (Boxes 6, 101)
    Studies, reports, handbooks, maps, photographs, diagrams, and printed matter relating to the political, economic, social, and military conditions in the Balkans (Albania, Bulgaria, Greece, and Yugoslavia) and to the location of strategic power plants and industries in Yugoslavia. Includes two intelligence reports on the Cetnik and partisan resistance movements in Yugoslavia prepared for the Allied Military headquarters, Balkans, and one folder of photocopies of underground literature (in Slovenian and Serbo-Croatian) relating to resistance activities in Yugoslavia during World War II. Includes declassified records returned to file after February 2016 release by Hoover.
  - Belgium (Box 46)
    - General, undated
      Pamphlet issued by the Belgian Information Center relating to the escape of two Belgian air officers to Great Britain by airplane and to conditions in Belgium.
    - Underground movements (Box 7)
      - 1939-1945
        Leaflets, posters, proclamations, press releases, underground literature, writings, and clippings. In French, Flemish, and English.
      - 1942-1945 (Box 8)
        Proclamations and miscellany relating to the resistance movement in German-occupied Belgium during World War II and to the entry of Allied troops into Brussels in September 1944. In French, Flemish, and German.
  - Burma (Box 45)
    - Burma Campaign, Japanese account
    - Burma Road, 1945 (Box 48)
      Pamphlet relating to the Burma Road through the China-Burma-India Theater.
    - Occupation of Rangoon by the Imperial Japanese Army, circa 1942
      Propaganda-style flyer announcing the "annihilation" of the American, British, Chinese and Dutch forces. Typed English translation is provided.
  - Czechoslovakia (Box 46)
    - General, 1943
      Pamphlet issued by Inter-Allied Publications, entitled Unknown Country: The Story of Czechoslovakia.
    - Underground movements, circa 1944, 1945 (Box 8)
      Two leaflets (mimeographed in Czech) issued by the resistance movement in German-occupied Czechoslovakia, and a translation (printed) of a clandestine Czech resistance pamphlet, entitled Svejk in the Protectorate.
  - Denmark
    - General
      Leaflets relating to the resistance movement in German-occupied Denmark during World War II and to the post-war reconstruction of Denmark.
    - Conditions, 1942 May - 1944 May (Box 53)
      Issues of The Danish Listening Post put out by the National America Denmark Association.
  - France (Boxes 8, 46)
    - General, 1942-1946
      Pamphlets, leaflets, serial issues, and miscellany. Includes both pro-Vichy and pro-resistance propaganda, blank forms for travel permit requests used in German-occupied France, and a few post-war political items. In French and German.
    - Refugees, 1943-1944 (Box 9)
      Correspondence and memoranda relating to the transportation of Spanish refugees in the vicinity of Toulouse to Germany for forced labor.
    - Resistance, 1940-1945 (Boxes 9-19)
      Underground materials, including memoranda, instructions, orders, reports, letters, maps, charts, clandestine newspapers, bulletins, and leaflets, distributed by various resistance groups. Boxes 17-19 contain duplicates.
  - Germany (Box 19)
    - General, 1934-1950
      Pamphlets, leaflets, serial issues, maps, manuals, and bulletins relating to Germany's participation in World War II and to its post-war status. Includes a few pre-war items relating to German fascism.
    - Administration of justice
      Miscellaneous lists, notes, and statistics relating to the administration of justice by German occupation authorities in the Netherlands during World War II. In German and Dutch.
    - Armed Forces (Box 46)
      - General, undated
        Handbook describing the economic status and rights of the German soldier.
      - Soldier's diary, 1944 May-September (Box 22)
        Holograph diary of an unidentified German soldier.
    - Conditions (Box 54)
      - General, 1940 May - 1941 June
        Issues of News Flashes from Germany.
      - Extracts from letters written by an unidentified anti-Nazi German, 1940 (Box 19)
      - Pamphlet by Erik Erikson, entitled Herrn Thomas Mann, relating to Thomas Mann and conditions in Germany during the war, undated (Box 46)
    - Forced labor, 1936-1945 (Boxes 20-22)
      Reports, memoranda, regulations, and miscellany relating to the importation and supervision of foreign workers in Germany during World War II. Includes some miscellaneous material relating to the structure of the Hitlerjugend and other Nazi organizations, and to Nazi racial ideology and historical and cultural outlook. See also: oversize Hitler Youth hierarchy diagram in map case.
    - Foreign policy, 1942 (Box 48)
      Pamphlet relating to German foreign policy from Otto von Bismarck to Adolf Hitler.
    - Prisoners of war, 1946 (Box 22)
      Photocopy of a typescript memoir authored by an unidentified German prisoner of war. Relates to conditions of imprisonment of German prisoners of war in Russia during World War II.
    - Rearmament, 1942 (Box 48)
      Pamphlet relating to Germany's secret air rearmament from 1919 to 1933.
    - Reconstruction, 1945 (Box 53)
      Pamphlets relating to prospects for democracy in post-war Germany and to industrial disarmament of aggressor states.
    - Resistance (Box 48)
      - General, 1944, undated
        Flyers and pamphlets relating to resistance among the German people.
      - National Committee "Free Germany,", undated (Box 46)
        Pamphlet by Siegbert Kahn relating to the Committee's activities, particularly its radio broadcasts to the German people.
      - Rote Kapelle (Box 22)
        Biographical notes relating to members of the German anti-Nazi resistance movement.
    - War crimes (Box 48)
      - General, 1941-1944
        Pamphlets, correspondence, and clippings relating to war crimes committed in various German-occupied European countries and to Allied demands for reparations. In English and Polish.
      - Nuremberg Trial, 1946 (Box 46)
        Pamphlet by Stephen Gorski relating to German war crimes and the Nuremberg Trial.
  - Great Britain (Boxes 23-33)
    - General, 1938-1946
      Pamphlets, serial issues, leaflets, bulletins, newsletters, maps, and posters relating to British politics, conditions in Great Britain during World War II, war aims, civil defense, the wartime economy, and post-war reconstruction. Includes issuances of various groups in Great Britain during the war.
    - Armed Forces, undated (Box 46)
      Brochure relating to coastal defense operations by the British Air Force.
    - Civil defense, 1942
      Manual, entitled We Shall Fight in the Streets! Guide to Street Fighting.
    - Prisoners of war, 1945? (Box 47)
      Pamphlet issued by the Allied Forces 21st Army Group entitled Guidance in Making Arrangements for Liberated British Prisoners of War.
  - Greece (Box 54)
    - General, 1941
      The American Friends of Greece, Greece 1821-1941.
    - Conditions, 1942 May - 1946 July
      Issues of the Greek War Relief Newsletter, put out by the Greek War Relief Association.
    - German occupation, 1942 (Box 48)
      Pamphlet relating to war crimes committed in Greece by Germany, Italy, and Bulgaria.
    - Resistance, 1941-1946 (Box 34)
      Leaflets and pamphlets relating to the Greek resistance movement.
  - Hungary, 1945
    Holograph diary of an unidentified Hungarian soldier.
  - Italy (Box 54)
    - General
      In Italian and English. Includes George A. Tesoro, The Bankruptcy of Fascist Economy through the Eyes of Italian Economists (1943).
    - Conditions, 1944 February-August
      Issues of Facts from Italy, put out by the Committee for a Democratic Foreign Policy.
    - Simoni, Simone, 1944 (Box 34)
      Clippings from Italian newspapers relating to the execution of S. Simoni, Italian Army General, by German occupation troops in Italy.
    - Underground movements (Box 46)
      - Issue of Cronache della regione Lombardia, relating to underground movements in Lombardy, 1974 September-October
      - Four leaflets urging Italians and Romans in particular to rise against fascism and the German occupation, 1944
  - Japan (Box 43)
    - Armed Forces
      Daily duty roster for some unidentified Japanese garrison quartered in an unknown location. Entries run from February 1 to 16.
    - Diplomatic history, 1941 December 8 (Box 34)
      Printed translation of the Japanese declaration of war on the U.S. and Great Britain.
    - Press
      Translations of articles from Japanese newspapers relating to world political, military, and diplomatic affairs during the first years of World War II.
    - Prisoners and prisons, 1942
      Proclamation issued by Japanese naval officials and relating to regulations for civilian prisoners of war captured at Wake Island and being transported from the island on Japanese naval vessels.
    - War economy, 1944-1945 (Box 101)
      Declassified records returned to file after February 2016 release by Hoover. Consists of two reports: "The Japanese Occupation Technique in the Field of Money and Banking," Foreign Economic Administration, Liberated Areas Branch, February 1944; and "Japan's War Economy, 1943-1944," Foreign Economic Administration, Special Areas Branch, Far East Enemy Division, February 1945. Also stamped Far Eastern Civil Affairs Training School at Stanford University.
  - Korea, 1945 April 17 (Box 101)
    Declassified records returned to file after February 2016 release by Hoover. Consists of a report, "Summary Industrial Survey of Korea," Foreign Economic Administration, Enemy Branch, Japanese Special Services Staff. Also stamped Far Eastern Civil Affairs Training School at Stanford University.
  - Latin America, circa 1939-1942 (Box 54)
    Mainly pro-Allied propaganda, especially from Mexico.
  - Netherlands (Box 34)
    - General
      - Miscellaneous memorabilia, satirical postcards, proclamations, and press clippings, 1942-1945
        Relates to the course of World War II in the Netherlands, including the German occupation, Allied propaganda, Dutch press coverage of the war, the liberation of Amsterdam on May 5, 1945, and photocopies of Dutch underground literature (in Dutch).
      - Ration cards (Box 54)
    - Forced labor, 1942 (Box 34)
      Three letters from Dutch workers transported to Germany for forced labor relating to working conditions in Germany.
    - German occupation
      - General, 1940-1945
        Proclamations, identification cards, registration forms and miscellany, issued by the German occupation authorities in the Netherlands, relating to regulations of the Dutch civilian population during World War II. In Dutch and German.
      - Administration of justice (see: Germany)
    - Liberation
      Proclamations issued by the Dutch and Allied military authorities relating to the entry of Allied troops into the Netherlands in 1945.
    - Prisoners of war
      Summaries of reports relating to the transportation of 2000 Dutch officers from the Netherlands to a prison camp in Germany in May 1942 and to living conditions in the camp.
    - Underground movements, 1944-1945
      Flyers, leaflets, proclamations, and newsletters.
  - Norway
    - General, 1939-1943
      Photocopies of letters to the editor of the San Francisco News, written by William Moler-Loswick and relating mainly to Norway during World War II.
    - Underground movements, circa 1940-1945
      Propaganda leaflets distributed by the resistance movement in German-occupied Norway during World War II. In German and Norwegian.
  - Philippines, undated (Box 35)
    Photostats of reports, memoranda, letters, and orders pertaining to the guerrilla warfare of Chinese volunteers in the Philippines against the Japanese during World War II. In English and Chinese.
  - Poland (Box 36)
    - General, 1942-1943
      Clippings from American daily newspapers and from Yiddish newspapers in the U.S., Canada, Mexico, Argentina, Uruguay, and South Africa relating to German atrocities in occupied Poland, persecution and extermination of Jews, activities of Polish emigre groups, and the case of Victor Alter and Henryk Erlich. In English and Yiddish.
    - Army, 1941 December (Box 54)
      Leaflets urging Poles in the Soviet Union to join the Anders Army.
    - German occupation, 1940-1944 (Box 48)
      Pamphlets relating to conditions in occupied Poland, German atrocities, the persecution and extermination of Jews, the Polish underground army and various resistance groups, and the Warsaw Uprising.
    - Underground movements, 1939-1944 (Box 37)
      Proclamations, underground literature, other printed matter, and charts relating to events and conditions in German-occupied Poland, especially to Polish resistance movements. In English, Polish, and German.
  - Romania, 1945 (Box 44)
    One book illustrated with photographs depicting the air battle of Ploesti (1944 April 5 - August 19).
  - Soviet Union (Box 37)
    - German occupation
      - General, 1941
        Proclamations relating to regulations imposed upon the civilian population by the German occupation authorities. In German, Russian, and Ukrainian.
      - Ukraine, 1984 (Box 48)
        Pamphlet relating to the invasion, occupation, and ultimate liberation of Ukraine in 1944.
    - Resistance (Box 44)
      Anti-Nazi cartoons by various Soviet artists. Captions in Russian and English.
  - Spain, 1946 April 17 (Box 46)
    Printed statement by Oscar Lange, Polish ambassador and delegate for Poland to the United Nations Security Council, at the meeting of the Security Council in New York.
  - United States (Boxes 54-56)
    - General, 1940-1946
      Pamphlets and newsletters relating to economic and social conditions in the United States and to the American government. Includes proceedings of the Eighth Pan American Child Congress, Washington, D.C., 1942 May 2-9.
    - African-Americans, 1943-1946 (Box 56)
      Pamphlets, conference proceedings, and newsletters. Includes issuances of the Congress of Racial Equality and the National Urban League.
    - Armed Forces (Boxes 39-41, 46)
      - General, 1941-1945
        Printed matter, including manuals and guidebooks issued by the U.S. Army and Navy, and pamphlets and guidebooks relating to the U.S. Armed Forces issued by commercial publishers during World War II. Includes manuals, handbooks, and regulations issued by the War Department, and a report on radar capabilities released by the joint Board on Scientific Information Policy.
      - Air Force, 1943, 1991 (Box 48)
        Booklet, entitled Target Germany: The Army Air Forces' Official Story of the VIII Bomber Command's First Year Over Europe; and booklet relating to the Air Force's report on the special bombing missions over Japan, 1945 July 20 - August 14. In English and Japanese.
      - Navy, 1944-1945 (Box 43)
        Communications and printed matter relating to the end of World War II in the Pacific. Includes an admission ticket to the San Francisco plenary session of the United Nations Conference on World Organization.
    - Foreign-born Americans, circa 1943, undated (Box 46)
      Pamphlet reprinting two speeches delivered at the Tenth Anniversary National Conference of the American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born, New York, 1943 October 30-31, relating to the contribution of foreign-born Americans to the war effort; and a pamphlet relating to Americans of German descent.
    - Foreign policy (Box 56)
      - General, 1941 April 7
        Speech by Ernest W. Gibson, "Should Our Ships Convoy Arms to Britain?"
      - Neutrality, 1940-1942 (Boxes 42, 56)
        Speeches and leaflets relating to American neutrality. Includes a broadside reproducing a leaflet (printed) mailed by B. K. Wheeler, U.S. Senator from Montana, urging U.S. neutrality in World War II, and letters (typewritten) in reply from two soldiers who received copies of the leaflet; and a speech by Robert S. Field.
    - Post-war period, 1944-1946 (Box 56)
      Pamphlets relating to plans for post-war economic conversion and social adjustment.
    - Prisoner of war camps, 1943-1944 (Box 42)
      Reports, press releases, lists, and miscellany relating to conditions in prisoner of war camps in the U.S. during World War II and to the exchange of U.S. and Axis civilian nationals in captivity.
    - Miscellany, 1941-1946, 1965 (Boxes 38, 44)